Okay, next we'll briefly consider queue implementations using
그러면, 이제 간단히 같은 기본적인 기저 자료구조를 활용한
the same basic underlying data structures.
큐 구현을 살펴보도록 합시다.
So here's the corresponding API for QueueOfStrings.
StackOfStrings와 대응되는 QueueOfStrings라는 API가 있는데요.
Actually it's the same API as for stacks, just the names are different.
스택과 똑같은 API를 제공합니다만, 연산의 이름이 다릅니다.
Instead of push we have enqueue instead of pop we have dequeue.
push 대신 enqueue를, pop 대신 dequeue를 쓰고 있죠.
And the semantics is different, for enqueue we add an item say at the end
그 의미(sementics)도 다른데, enqueue는 큐 끝에 아이템을 넣는 것이고요.
of the queue, and for dequeue we remove an item from the beginning.
dequeue는 큐 시작에서 아이템을 제거하는 겁니다.
It's as if you're waiting in line to buy a ticket.
실생활의 유사 사례를 들어보면, 티켓을 사기 위해 줄서있는 상황인데,
When you're enqueue you go at the end, and
enqueue를 하면 여러분이 줄 끝에 서는 거죠.
when the one that's been in there the longest is the one that comes off.
반면 dequeue의 대상은 그 줄에서 가장 오래 기다렸던 사람인 거고요.
So lets look at how we implement those, first using linked list and then arrays.
이를 어떻게 구현할 지를 처음엔 연결 리스트로 다음엔 배열으로 살펴봅시다.
So now our representation of a queue with a length list,
먼저 연결 리스트 기반의 큐 표현을 살펴볼건데요.
we need to maintain two pointers, references.
두 개의 포인터, 즉 참조를 유지합니다.
One, to the first item in the list and the other to the last item in the list.
하나느 리스트의 첫 아이템을, 다른 하나는 리스트의 마지막 아이템을 가리킵니다.
When we insert,
아이템을 삽입하면,
we're going to add the item at the end of the list instead of at the beginning.
리스트의 시작점이 아니라 리스트의 끝에 아이템을 삽입하고요.
And when we remove, we'll do the same, we'll take it off at the front.
제거를 할 때는, 기존과 똑같이 시작점에서 제거를 합니다.
So here's the implementation of dequeue.
여기에 dequeue의 구현이 있습니다.
It's identical to the code for pop for a stack.
스택에서의 pop과 코드가 동일합니다.
We save away the item, we delete the first node by advancing the reference and
아이템을 떼어서 저장해두고, 참조를 진전시켜 first가 가리키던 노드를 삭제하고,
then we return the item, so identical.
그 뒤에 아이템을 리턴합니다. 그러니 똑같죠.
To add a note, or enqueue, add a new note to a linked-list.
노드를 삽입하려면, 즉 enqueue하려면, 즉 연결 리스트에 새 노드를 삽입하는 걸 말하는 건데
We want to put it at the end, so that will be the last one returned.
리스트의 끝에 넣어야 할테고, 따라서 참조 last가 마지막에 갱신되어야 합니다.
So we, to add it at the end, so
따라서 마지막에 아이템을 넣기 위해서는
first thing we need to do is save a link, the last node.
처음 해야 할 것은 마지막 노드의 참조를 oldlast에 저장하는 겁니다.
We're going to need that because we need to change it's reference
oldlast를 저장해야 하는 이유는, 기존 마지막 노드의 next 변수,
from null to point to the new node.
즉 null 상태로 되어 있을 참조가 새 노드를 가리키게 해야 하기 때문입니다.
Then we'll create a new node for the end of the list.
그럼 이제 연결 리스트 끝에 새 노드를 만듭시다.
We'll populate its fields and then that old link
새 마지막 노드에 아이템을 삽입하고 참조 next를 null로 초기화를 했다면
will change that from null to a pointer to the new node.
기존 마지막 노드 oldlast의 참조 next가 새 노드를 가리키도록 변경합니다.
So again, just a few lines of code,
다시 말해, 몇 줄의 코드이지만
[COUGH] that's basic linked-list processing.
이것이 기본적인 연결 리스트 처리 과정입니다.
Actually years ago when we taught courses in algorithms and data structures,
사실 몇 년 전에 (C언어 등을 사용하는) 알고리즘과 자료구조를 가르칠 때에는
much of the course would be about this kind of pointer manipulation.
많은 강의들이 이런 포인터의 교묘한 처리에 집중했었습니다.
But nowadays that's restricted to just a few implementations like stack and
하지만 요즘은 스택과 큐 같은 몇몇 구현이나 기본 자료 구조에서만
queue and a few other fundamental data structures.
사용되고 있습니다.
So we don't need so much any more general programs for manipulating linked-lists.
이 수업에서는 연결 리스트를 취급하는 더 일반적인 프로그램을 그리 다루진 않을 겁니다.
We encapsulate them in basic data types like these.
지금처럼 기본 데이터 타입이 연결 리스트를 취급하는 캡슐화를 할 겁니다.
All right, so let's go back to our full implementation and
좋습니다. 이제 전체 구현으로 가서
this is just taking care of collecting the code from the previous slides.
기존 슬라이드의 코드를 살펴모아 봅시다.
But also taking care of special cases when the queue is empty.
큐가 비어있는 특별한 경우를 고려해야 하기도 하고요.
To make sure that if the queue is empty after we move an item
dequeue를 한 뒤에 큐가 비어있다면, 이를 명확하게 하기 위해 last를 null로 설정해야 합니다.
we gotta set last to null.
그래서 last를 null로 설정했고요.
Make sure that both first and last are always what we want them to be.
first와 last가 우리가 기대하는 바대로 동작하도록 하기 위함이죠.
So those are details that are easy to check.
상세는 여러분 스스로 체크하실 수 있을 겁니다.
Okay, what about arrays?
배열은 어떨까요?
Well, we won't do the details, but
상세는 다루지 않겠습니다만,
it's not difficult to implement queues with resizing arrays as well.
배열 리사이징을 이용한 큐를 만드는 게 그리 어렵진 않을 겁니다.
Not difficult, but
어렵지 않아요.
a definitely tricky programming exercise that people are welcome to try.
하지만 여러분들이 해볼 만한, 까다로운 프로그래밍 연습문제임은 분명합니다.
So we'll maintain two pointers, the first item in the queue and
두 포인터 (인덱스), 즉 큐의 처음 아이템을 가리키는 head와
the tail, which is the position for the next item to appear.
다음 아이템이 들어갈 장소를 가리키는 tail을 유지해야 합니다.
So for enqueue, you add a new item a tail.
enqueue 연산에서는 tail에 새 아이템을 삽입합니다.
And for dequeue you remove an item for a head.
dequeue 연산에서는 head가 가리키는 아이템을 삭제합니다.
And the trick is that once you get past the capacity,
까다로운 부분은 연산 과정에서 인덱스가 배열의 용량을 넘어섰을 때
you have to reset back to zero.
인덱스가 0으로 초기화되어야 한다는 점입니다.
And so that's a little extra code, and
약간의 추가 코드가 필요한데요.
then you have to add the resizing capability as well to
스택과 같은 자료구조로 구현하기 위해서
implement the data structure the same as for stack.
배열 리사이징을 추가할 수도 있을 겁니다.
And we'll leave that as an exercise.
이런 부분은 연습문제로 남겨두겠습니다.